Now it is time to start building a little more
complex machine language assembly language
applications. And as always, these slides are not
necessarily the best reference. Once you listen
to them, you should probably start looking at
the online documentation that I provide for the
CDC 6504. So we'll start with another review of
the architecture. By now, this should be pretty
familiar to you. We have a program counter which
is telling us where in the instruction memory to
retrieve the next instruction. We have the
accumulator register which is kind of the
most flexible register. We have the Z and the N
flags that tell us whether last thing we did in
a register was zero or negative or a compare
instruction. The X and the Y registers are
registers that are a little less capable than
the accumulator. We show instruction memory in
base 2 and data memory we show in hex because it
usually contains ASCII. So there is a new thing
that's only in assembly. Labels are something
that's as uh only in assembly and this data
directive is the thing that's only in assembly.
Everything we've done so far in the assembler is
populating the instruction memory by parsing the
instruction the assembly language instructions
and producing the zeros and ones that are the
machine language. But there's also this thing
called a DATA directive where we can fill the
data memory up with some preloaded data. Before
the program starts we load there's a step called
"loading". We load the program into the memory can
load the instruction memory and we can preload the
data memory with this data directive but it's not
machine code it is something that assemblers do
and give us a loadable image that includes a data
segment basically and it can either be a quoted
string or a series of hex digits and We mostly
will use quoted strings. So you can print hello
world by having a single line of machine language
break which means halt and but then have the data
filled with hello world. And it just turns out
that the emulator dumps out the data when it's all
done. So this is the simplest program. It's not
really machine language, but it's the simplest
program in the emulator to make it print hello
world. So here's just a couple. So in this one
we're going to add 27 + 15 and then store it in
memory location zero. So we load 27 an immediate
immediate constant into the accumulator. Then we
add 15 which is another immediate constant. So
that's 42. And then we're going to store that in
location memory location zero. So you can see by
the and then we halt. So by the time the program
counter makes to zero 05 hex there is a single
0x2A which is 42 and hex and then you can see that
that prints out asterisk because if you go look
at your ASCII chart asterisk is 42 decimal. Our
next example is just printing hello and so we're
going to end up putting this in memory so that
the program will dump out the memory starting at
memory location zero after the program finishes.
So, we do an immediate load of the letter H
and we store it in memory location zero. We
do an immediate load of the letter E, store
that in location one. We do immediate load of
the letter L and store that in location two. And
then we store that again in location three because
there's two L's. Then we do a immediate load
of the letter O and we store that in location
four. And then we quit. And then if you look at
the memory, there is H E L L O in the memory in
hex. And then you can see that the program prints
HELLO out when it's all done. And again, this
is just exploring some assembly language/machine
language. So now we're going to do a little more
complicated and a little more practical example.
So we are going to uppercase a whole string of
characters and we're going to take the characters
from memory, read them all from memory in a loop,
check them, convert them to uppercase, and then
store them back if necessary. So the key to this
is our data is going to be preloaded using the
data directive in memory locations 0 through 4.
And that's the lower hello with a h upper-cased
already. So now we've run it. You can see the
status is halted. And you see that it printed
out an uppercase hello. And the only real thing
that it changed was memory location 1 2 3 and 4
are now the uppercase versions of those letters.
Now before we go through that code in some
detail, let's think about uppercasing this
string in other languages. Now if you're a Python
person be like "Hello".upper. There's a method.
"Hello" the string is an object and you can call a
method upper(). Now it's not changing the Hello to
HELLO. It is just giving you a copy of that. Now
if we didn't have upper, we would have some pretty
ugly Python. So, you can't change a Python string
in place. So, you have to make a variable. In this
case, I'll call it me because it's like the
memory, but you can't change mem in Python.
You got to make a new one. So, then we're going
to have this for loop for XR, which kind of is
my way of saying X register is range len of mem.
That's going to run XR through zero through four
up to but not including uh five. And then we're
going to retrieve memory one character of memory
from XR to XR + one. Put that in the accumulator.
And if the accumulator is greater than or equal
to A and less than or equal to Z means it's
between A and Z inclusive then we're going to
compute the new character. And now you you'll see
this chr and ord. And the problem is is that in
Python we're not even using ASCII. The "Hello"
is Unicode. So ord says give me the ordinal of
the current character I'm looking at subtract the
ordinal of a lower case a and adding the ordinal
uppercase a. Now, this wouldn't necessarily work
for any set of characters because Unicode can
have a lot of things and so the actual uppercase
is a little more complex inside of Python. So,
we've computed the uppercase character if we
know it's a lowercase character by mathematics
and then we append it to the new version of the
memory building that up one string at a time and
then we print it out. And so you can't even
do this because Python is not really designed
for low-level array like things. Lists are not
arrays. Although if you took my C programming
class, you would understand that they're kind of
arrays. Okay. So let's take a look at this in C,
which is a lot more like assembly language.
So if we take a look at the top of this,
we include the stdio.h and we have a main program
and we use the register register int star ac. Now
for those of you who don't know C, the register
is a is a keyword in the C language and it says
this is going to be something that I'm going to
want to make high performance. So put it in a
register if you possibly can. Then I'm going
to create a character array named mem. Now,
this is going to be a six character array with
a zero termination. The letters "Hello" followed
by a zero. And so then what we're saying is we're
saying for xr equals zero as long as mem sub xr,
we're now looking for that zero terminated
string. As long as me xr is non zero,
continue. And then add one to xr. So then we take
our that's our index variable - our loop iteration
variable. So we say let's take the accumulator and
load in memory sub xr because xr is our sort of
index variable and in this case we're dealing with
ASCII and we know it. So if uh the accumulator
minus a is less than zero we continue and if
you recall and see the continue does mean that
the increment part of the for loop is executed
XR++. if not we're just going to say M memory sub
XR equals the accumulator minus 0x20. So we're
doing the case conversion there and putting it
right back into memory. That for loops runs five
times and then we print out the uppercase. So now
we are going to finally walk through the assembly
language version of this. So I've got the code on
the left and I've got the before memory and the
after memory on the right. Now one of the things
that you'll notice is that I have given you on
on the right hand side I've given you the sort of
pseudo code for the C code that corresponds to the
assembly language that we're going to do. So we're
going to effectively construct a for loop that's
going to loop through an array of characters. So
the first thing we do is we're going to set X to
zero with CLX and then we're going to have a label
to come back up to the top of our for loop. The
next instruction LDA $00, X is the new instruction
we haven't used so far and this is an indexed
load into the accumulator. The dollar 0 is the
starting address and the X register contains our
offset. So it basically adds X to wherever we're
at and then that becomes the address and then
we're going to load that into the accumulator.
Now, that act of loading into the accumulator
is going to set the Z flag and the N flag as any
change to any register does. And so, we're going
to use a BEQ, which is really kind of branch zero.
That means if the accumulator is zero, we're
going to follow the branch. But in this case,
the accumulator is going to have uppercase H
0x48. And so, BEQ is not going to branch. So,
we're going to fall through. And then we're
going to start our if test in a sense. Compare
the accumulator to lowercase a. Now recall that
in ASI uppercase A is less than lowercase A in
the ASCII chart. So if it's already uppercase
that comparison is going to be minus, right?
It's going to be negative and so we're going to
branch to in effect a label that I called cont,
which is sort of like a continue. We're going to
skip the subtract if it's already an uppercase.
So, BMI skips the subtraction if it's already
uppercase. Then we come into the continue label
and then we are incrementing X. Now remember that
continue actually runs the increment of a for
loop. And then we're going to jump back up to the
top of the loop, but X is now one. And now we're
going to load index load from at location zero
with X of one. And so now we get the 0x65, which
is the lowercase e. And we're going to check to
see if we're out of the loop. We're not so we're
going to fall through. We're going to compare
the lowercase e to lowercase a. And in this case,
it's not minus because e is greater than a.
And so we're going to do the subtraction. So,
we're going to convert that to uppercase by
subtracting 20 hex. And then we're going to
start right back into that location, which
is location zero indexed by the X register,
which is one. And so that's going to put 0x45 into
location 0x01. Then we drop into the continue. We
add one to X. The X register becomes two and we
jump to the top of the loop. So you see that how
this is kind of working, right? So now X is two.
And so we do an index load of of location 0 + 2
branch if it's equal to done. Check to see if it's
uppercase already. And in this case it's not. we
subtract. So at some point you can follow this. It
will go round and round until we get to an offset
of five. Jump to the top of the loop. We're going
to load location zero plus x which is five. And
in this case it's going to be a zero. And then the
BEQ is going to be true in a sense. And then we're
going to jump to done. And then the application
is going to finish and print out its after data
which is fully upper cased hello. That's a bunch
of assembly language and C and Python. And I would
say that you're going to spend a bunch of time
with the emulator and a bunch of time with the
emulator documentation. And hopefully with
some time this will all make sense to you.